<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/styles/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

<title>Exeami blogs</title>
<subtitle type="html">My recent works can be found here. To know me more, go to &lt;a href="https://exeami.com"&gt;exeami.com&lt;/a&gt;</subtitle>
<link rel="self" href="https://exeami.com/blogs/feed/" />
<updated>2023-10-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
<author>
  <name>Exeami</name>
  <email>contact@exeami.com</email>
  <uri>https://exeami.com/</uri>
</author>
<icon>https://exeami.com/images/logos/exeami-with-bg.webp</icon>
<id>https://exeami.com/</id>

  <entry>
    <title>Implementing search for a website</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://exeami.com/blogs/add-search-for-website"/>
    <id>https://exeami.com/blogs/add-search-for-website</id>
    <updated>2023-10-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>The way I implemented in-house search for my website</summary>
    <content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
		</content>
    
    <author>
			<name>Exeami</name>
			<email>exeami@proton.me</email>
		</author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Instagram for kids</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://exeami.com/blogs/instagram-for-kids"/>
    <id>https://exeami.com/blogs/instagram-for-kids</id>
    <updated>2023-09-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>Reasons to avoid creating instagram for kids</summary>
    <content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
  If you have an Instagram account for your babies or plan to have one, I want you to think twice before doing it.
  Most of us are immature and innocent and follow the trend without being fully aware that some things we share on the
  internet might be bad for us and our loved ones in many ways.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I want to point out a few reasons why sharing too much about kids online is not a good idea.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Consent&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When sharing personal details, pictures and day-to-day activities of your kids online, you are creating
      a personally identifiable &lt;strong&gt;permanent digital footprint&lt;/strong&gt; of them whether they like it or not. I
      feel that kids
      should have a right to their digital privacy, as some of these details or fame might change events in their
      lives the way they don&#x27;t want them to be, and they might not even be able to change it.
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Safety&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Everyone wants to safeguard and protect their kids as they love them, and it&#x27;s their duty, and they are
      responsible for the kid&#x27;s safety. Predators, stalkers, and paedophiles are all over the internet. It&#x27;s an easy
      way to get
      the information, so please don&#x27;t be the one who provides it. I heard some parents sharing full names, locations,
      school names, bus timings, activities, and everything on social media that can become a huge safety concern. If
      not, the photo you thought was cute might expose your kids to bullies.
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Misuse&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The photos you share can be misappropriated and reused, or others use them for commercial purposes without your
      knowledge. &lt;a href=&quot;https://firewalltimes.com/instagram-data-breach-timeline/&quot;&gt;Do not think that just because
        you have a private account, you can control who gets access to the photos.&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Comparison&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Based on the &lt;a href=&quot; https://doi.org/10.1038/s44271-023-00013-0&quot;&gt;DIPF | Leibniz Institute for Research and
        Information in Education, and Center for Research on Individual Development and Adaptive Education of Children
        at Risk (IDeA)&lt;/a&gt; paper demonstrating that upward social
      comparison, comparing with people
      we consider to be socially better off is associated with reduced
      well-being such as lower life satisfaction or more depressive symptoms. The better the lives of others on social
      media, the worse we feel. Many parents compare parenting standards and doubt themselves. Many feel depressed
      when
      they get fewer likes on their baby&#x27;s pictures. This is not only bad for your mental health but also affects the
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/2156869320912520&quot;&gt;child&#x27;s well-being in the long
        term.&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Discomfort&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How much time do you spend getting the right picture with perfect lighting? How many photos are you taking? And
      how much time are you editing and trying to make it the best? And are you doing this for fun or for
      likes and comments? Taking a few pictures on occasion is good, but when we fall into the trap of
      being emotionally attached to the engagement of our posts, we might end up causing discomfort to our loved ones
      by unconsciously forcing them to do things that they don&#x27;t want to do.
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Some parents might be doing this for commercial reasons, I don&#x27;t have a say in it. But if you are doing it as
  everyone
  else doing it or for making a digital album and sharing it with close friends and family. I recommend sharing on an
  end-to-end encrypted channel like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.signal.org/&quot;&gt;Signal&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The above applies if you only post photos of your children to your personal account, and you shouldn&#x27;t feel a
  false sense of protection. I focused on sperate account, as this means you plan to share a lot.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Always ask yourself if it is needed or worth the attention and virtual fame before posting anything about your
  babies online. Stay safe.
&lt;/p&gt;
		</content>
    
    <author>
			<name>Exeami</name>
			<email>contact@exeami.com</email>
		</author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting to know IndieWeb</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://exeami.com/blogs/getting-to-know-indie-web"/>
    <id>https://exeami.com/blogs/getting-to-know-indie-web</id>
    <updated>2023-09-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>Introduction to indieweb and reasons why we need it</summary>
    <content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
  Once I was reading about how Amazon gave a platform for many small businesses to sell products online and how it
  helped them. You might even have heard that, but think about it, whenever we buy something from a small business on
  Amazon, we often relate it as we bought it from Amazon and never really remember the seller or the creator. This
  might seem trivial, but imagine if you were a seller of handmade crafts on Amazon and you had a loyal customer base
  and a good reputation. What if
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://the-digital-reader.com/amazon-is-still-banning-authors-for-no-reason/&quot;&gt;Amazon suddenly banned you
    from selling on their platform&lt;/a&gt;,
  and you lost your source
  of income and your hard work? Or what if you had to &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/leticiamiranda/amazon-sellers-say-the-tech-giant-is-crushing-them-with&quot;&gt;lower
    your prices to compete with other sellers?&lt;/a&gt; Or &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/gadgets-news/amazon-imposes-new-fee-on-sellers-shipping-their-own-products/articleshow/102833427.cms&quot;&gt;pay
    a fee to
    Amazon and limit your profit margin?&lt;/a&gt;
  Or what if you couldn&#x27;t sell your products anywhere else for &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/news/amazon-keeps-prices-artificially-high-210059691.html&quot;&gt;a lower price than on
    Amazon&lt;/a&gt;
  , and you were stuck with their rules? Or
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.sky.com/story/amazon-sellers-fear-bankruptcy-after-rule-change-12936803&quot;&gt;they suddenly change
    terms and don&#x27;t pay you?&lt;/a&gt;
  Amazon is one of many examples to show the control of big corporations have on us.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Every &lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/silo&quot;&gt;silo&lt;/a&gt; site which is not yours, your data might feel like yours, but it
  is not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;https://bradfrost.com/blog/post/write-on-your-own-website/&quot; class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &quot;Writing on your own website associates your thoughts and ideas with you as a person. Having a distinct website
    design helps strengthen that association. Writing for another publication, you get a little circular avatar at the
    beginning of the post and a brief bio at the end of the post, and that&#x27;s about it. People will remember the
    publication, but probably not your name.&quot;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;quote-footer&quot;&gt;
    &lt;cite&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradfrost.com/blog/post/write-on-your-own-website/&quot;&gt;—Brad Frost on
        Write on your own website
      &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/cite&gt;
  &lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  When you know this, you want to change it and do something to change it. You also want your loved ones to be aware
  of it and own their data. The good news is, you are not alone. It&#x27;s wonderful to connect with people who share your
  vision and work together for a better future. When I first got to know about IndieWeb It felt like a hope.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is IndieWeb?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;As Indie web is about ownership, Your content is yours, and You are in control.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;https://indieweb.org/&quot; class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &quot;The IndieWeb is a community of independent &amp; personal websites connected by simple
    standards, based on the principles of: owning your domain &amp; using it as your primary identity, publishing on your
    ownsite (optionally syndicating elsewhere), and owning your data.&quot;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer class=&quot;quote-footer&quot;&gt;
    &lt;cite&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/&quot;&gt;— IndieWeb &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/cite&gt;
  &lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why do we need IndieWeb?&lt;/h3&gt;
There are many reasons why It is good to have your space on the web where you own what is yours. I am just listing
down a few.
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    If you do not want to part of social media where the more you spend time and contribute, &lt;a
      href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Targeted_advertising&quot;&gt;the more they learn about you
      and sell you&lt;/a&gt; (sell your browsing habits to advertisers).
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    If you don&#x27;t want Silos, control your experience of the web and decide &lt;a
      href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Filter_bubble&quot;&gt;what you see&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
      href=&quot;https://www.currentaffairs.org/2020/12/how-seo-is-gentrifying-the-internet&quot;&gt;where your content goes.&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    If you don&#x27;t want to be part of evil where once you create a community, they keep it under paywall or
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/login_wall&quot;&gt;authwall&lt;/a&gt; and
    leave you
    choose to &lt;a
      href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2023/6/20/23767848/reddit-blackout-api-protest-moderators-suspended-nsfw&quot;&gt;obey
      their rules or lose the community.&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    If you &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesun.ie/tech/11271562/instagram-users-lose-accounts-taylor-swift/&quot;&gt;don&#x27;t want to
      need permission&lt;/a&gt; to communicate, create and innovate with people around the globe with the
    internet.
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    If you don&#x27;t want to &lt;a
      href=&quot;https://www.howtogeek.com/403769/what-happens-to-your-digital-property-when-a-company-goes-out-of-business/&quot;&gt;
      lose all your data because the company gone out of business.&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    If you want to show that you are not consumed by the Silos.
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    If you want different monetization for your content in your way.
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/images/blogs/getting-to-know-indie-web/xkcd.webp&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;quote-footer&quot;&gt;
    &lt;cite&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com/1150/&quot;&gt;—xkcd - 1150&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/cite&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;It&#x27;s not just ownership&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/personal-domain&quot;&gt;Identity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Having a personal domain, which is the initial step of Indie web. It helps you to have more credibility,
    improves personal branding and makes it easy to find you.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/POSSE&quot;&gt;Syndication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;If you want to let your friends read your posts, their way using social media like Instagram, Tumblr, Twitter
    etc. You can post content on your site and publish links to 3rd party silos using POSSE (Publish (on your) Own
    Site, Syndicate Elsewhere) And can back feed the post activity back to your website. Now we can have all in one
    place, IndieWeb comments, and comments on your POSSE copies.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/Webmention&quot;&gt;Web Mentions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Web Mentions is a simple communication protocol between websites that enables cross-site conversations and
    website can display comments, likes, or other response. With Web mentions you are better connected, you decide
    what and how to display the interaction on the content you own.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/IndieAuth&quot;&gt;IndieAuth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;IndieAuth provides the ability to use your website (domain) to authenticate yourself on the web using a
    federated login protocol for Web sign-in.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/microformats&quot;&gt;MicroFormats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt; Add Microformats to your existing HTML to use structured data from your site to allow tools like feed readers.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Finally, It can be easy too…&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I know many might think,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is easy to create a silo account and post what they want with few steps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am not a celebrity or a company to own a domain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am not a web developer and I don&#x27;t know how to do it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  There can many reasons and excuses we give ourselves to start. Even I am new to this, yet to understand a lot. Having
  a sense of ownership gives pleasure and made me take my first step, you can find yours.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  There are many &lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/tools&quot;&gt;tools&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/Getting_Started&quot;&gt;step-by-step guides&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/discuss&quot;&gt;help&lt;/a&gt; available in
  the community to make it easy. Many smart people are
  contributing to make it easier so that we can own what is ours.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Do it for yourself, have fun and pride creating something that is yours, and It will get easy.
&lt;/p&gt;
		</content>
    
    <author>
			<name>Exeami</name>
			<email>contact@exeami.com</email>
		</author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why should I care about data privacy?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://exeami.com/blogs/data-privacy"/>
    <id>https://exeami.com/blogs/data-privacy</id>
    <updated>2020-07-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>Few reasons why we should care about data privacy</summary>
    <content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
  Recently when I was speaking about data privacy to a friend, he said &quot;How do I get affected if my data is collected,
  in a way I am getting personal suggestions, so it seems to be good, as I have nothing to hide?&quot;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  We usually listen to this in various forms, from many people around us, so I want to bring this up to you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The way we think about privacy is misleading.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  You might say, how can I watch a song of my favourite singer last night can possibly affect me? Or things I search
  for my academic project will harm me?
  It&#x27;s not the bits of data, but the complete profile of you, collected from different sources. All of it combined can
  provide a detailed profile of you that even you didn&#x27;t know of.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reasons-heading&quot;&gt;Why is it harmful?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;

  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Protect your freedom of thought&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have you ever heard of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawthorne_effect&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&quot;Hawthorne
        Effect&quot;&lt;/a&gt;? Let me tell you, people behave differently if they know they are being watched.

      If I say, &quot;you are exploring things about your sexuality or religious beliefs or medical problems today may cause
      you
      to
      lose your dream job after 10 years or a maybe physical threat to you or your family by unacceptable society,
      will
      you
      do that?&quot;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      This is not hoaxed, your employer with your profile in hand with opposite beliefs can target you and your
      comment
      on
      some social media might keep your life at risk by the mob.

      The point is, if you don&#x27;t have the privacy to do this kind of self-exploration,
      you aren&#x27;t free.
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Price Discrimination&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &quot;Relevant ads are nice, at least I am not seeing some lipstick ad which I am least interested to watch&quot;, says
      one
      of
      my friends. It would be fine if you decided to give up this information for tangible benefits, right?

      If I say these exciting bargains are everything personal about you: your age, income, family&#x27;s ages, and income,
      medical history, dietary habits, favourite websites, your birthday...the list goes on and may never
      see a benefit aside from this ad, and no ones including you in the decision.
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Identity theft&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Identity_theft&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Identity theft&lt;/a&gt; is usually done for
      financial gain, but it will be possible to steal your sensitive data from your accounts as well as those
      belonging
      to your family, friends and can use your credentials to harm your reputation or cause online public
      humiliation.
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Privacy is a Human right&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      Not caring about it shows little knowledge about the history and the importance of it.

      It&#x27;s a human right just like the right to equality, to justice, freedom, a nationality, the right to religion,
      etc.

      It&#x27;s your Data, it exists because you exist, and you have complete right on every byte of it, playing around
      psychologically to steal data or to use it without your consent for personal gain, making you a fool
      by hiding things is not right and never will be.

      Simply it&#x27;s &lt;strong&gt;NOT ETHICAL&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;The creepers&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      How do you feel if someone is constantly listening to you when you are discussing a sensitive or personal
      topic?

      I will say it&#x27;s happening right now. Your own devices, you got for your convenience, are spying on you.

      Sometimes a user, by default, is opted into being tracked by the listening devices (aka personal assistants like
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newsweek.com/amazon-alexa-recordings-romania-sex-privacy-1452173&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alexa&lt;/a&gt;,
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://nypost.com/2019/07/29/apples-siri-routinely-records-you-having-sex/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Siri&lt;/a&gt;,
      and &lt;a href=&quot;https://money.cnn.com/2017/10/11/technology/google-home-mini-security-flaw/index.html&quot;
        target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Google Home&lt;/a&gt;) which records your private conversations without your consent.
      And are being listened by not just some algorithm, but by a human.
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;The Filter bubble&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;


  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; Did we talk about personal suggestions? They are good, right? what possibly can be bad about having the things
      on
      the
      plate which we want? Check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Filter_bubble&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&quot;filter
        bubble&quot;&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      Filter bubbles refer to the state of intellectual isolation that can result from personalized searches on search
      engines or social media sites. As a result,&lt;strong&gt;&lt;i&gt; users become separated from most information that
          presents
          an
          opposing viewpoint.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      If I say for example you don&#x27;t want to wear a mask and if you search about it, if this filter bubble shows you
      the
      things which might bad for wearing a mask and make your opinion stronger and make you feel good, but if you
      don&#x27;t
      know the use of that it might make your life risky.
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  These are just six good reasons to care about data privacy, there are a lot more things we need to
  worry
  about.
  we will meet again here, as privacy cannot be covered in a single blog post.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I want to conclude with Edward Snowden&#x27;s quote,
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;content-box&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&quot;Arguing that you don&#x27;t care about the right to privacy because you have nothing to
    hide,
    is
    no
    different from saying you don&#x27;t care about free speech because you have nothing to say.&quot;&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
		</content>
    
    <author>
			<name>Exeami</name>
			<email>contact@exeami.com</email>
		</author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Homomorphic Encryption</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://exeami.com/blogs/homomorphic-encryption"/>
    <id>https://exeami.com/blogs/homomorphic-encryption</id>
    <updated>2020-04-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>Brief introduction on Homomorphic Encryption</summary>
    <content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homomorphic_encryption&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Homomorphic Encryption&lt;/a&gt; is an
  encryption technique where we can perform computations on encrypted data and get the result which will be encrypted
  and can be decrypted only by the owner with the secret key.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why would anyone need Homomorphic Encryption?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Consider the scenario where you want some computation to be performed on some metadata
  with the help of third-party services, but you don&#x27;t want to expose your or your user&#x27;s data for security or
  privacy concerns.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The best &lt;i&gt;(and currently known)&lt;/i&gt; use case would be on cloud computing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The major scope of Homomorphic encryption can be in Genomics, Medical History, Finance, and wherever we deal
  with very sensitive private data but needs to perform some basic operations on a more generalized
  metadata.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A bit of history&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The problem of constructing a fully homomorphic encryption scheme was first proposed in 1978 - within a year of
  publishing of the RSA scheme.
  But Fully homomorphic system was not described until 2009, when computer scientist &lt;strong&gt;Craig Gentry&lt;/strong&gt;
  published thesis on &lt;a href=&quot;https://crypto.stanford.edu/craig/&quot;&gt;‘Fully Homomorphic Encryption using ideal
    lattices&#x27;.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  The major challenge now computational time. Many research activities are going on to speed up the process by
  decreasing the computational overhead that&#x27;s required for homomorphic encryption. The encryption in actual
  homomorphic
  schemes&#x27; functions are considerably more complicated, often they use a mathematical calculation involving lattices
  with a high number of dimensions, called the &lt;a
    href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ring_learning_with_errors&quot;&gt;Ring-Learning With Errors (RLWE) problem.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Availability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Several open-source implementations of homomorphic encryption schemes exist today.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/shaih/HElib&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;HELib&lt;/a&gt;: An early and widely used library
    from IBM that supports the BGV scheme and bootstrapping.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Microsoft/SEAL&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Microsoft SEAL&lt;/a&gt;: A widely used open
    source library from Microsoft that supports the BFV and the CKKS schemes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gchq/Palisade&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PALISADE&lt;/a&gt;: A widely-used open source
    library from a consortium of DARPA-funded defense contractors that provides lattice cryptography building blocks
    and supports leading homomorphic encryption schemes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Though the encryption scheme has been known from many years, because of complicated computations, we don&#x27;t
  have an optimal and practical solution yet. Hope we see the Fully Homomorphic encryption within a few decades
  with a wider scope.
&lt;/p&gt;
		</content>
    
    <author>
			<name>Exeami</name>
			<email>contact@exeami.com</email>
		</author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why should I switch to Signal?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://exeami.com/blogs/why-should-i-switch-to-signal"/>
    <id>https://exeami.com/blogs/why-should-i-switch-to-signal</id>
    <updated>2020-02-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>Reasons to switch to Signl messaging app and it's features</summary>
    <content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.signal.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Signal&lt;/a&gt; is a messaging app by Open Whisperer Systems,
    just like WhatsApp or iMessage or Facebook Messenger, but one that&#x27;s geared towards privacy and security. It&#x27;s
    encrypted, simple, and free.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Signal Vs WhatsApp&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
    They both use the same underlying encryption &quot;the Signal Protocol&quot; but drastically differ
    in terms of underlying philosophy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    WhatsApp can&#x27;t see what&#x27;s inside the messages, but they can see who is sending a message to whom and
    when - which is a large risk.
    And according to the WhatsApp privacy policy, &lt;strong&gt;the company reserves the right to record this
        information, known as message metadata&lt;/strong&gt;, and give it to governments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;The only data Signal retains is the phone number you register with and when you last logged
        into their server.&lt;/strong&gt;
    That&#x27;s it. It doesn&#x27;t even record the hour, minute, or second - only the day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    Signal is open-source and funded by donors, on the other hand WhatsApp is owned by Facebook, leaves users
    to being nothing more than another data collection point for Facebook for ad-targeting.
    WhatsApp was a messaging app first and added the security features later. Signal was all about security
    first. Because of this, WhatsApp has more now-traditional chat features. Both Signal and WhatsApp also include
    voice calling and video calling to round out the messaging apps.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image media-figure is-1-by-2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/why-should-i-switch-to-signal/signal_app.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Signal app image&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
        width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;342&quot;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
    Signal has plenty of features too including GIFs, can send your location, and Signal even has disappearing
    messages.Even voice calls on Signal are encrypted and screenshots can be disabled.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Signal, the non-profit organization, points out that &quot;there are no ads, no affiliate marketers, no
    creepy tracking&quot;, and it&#x27;s hard to ask for much more than that in terms of privacy. And It&#x27;s recommended by
    Edward Snowden.
    When you have an alternative which doesn&#x27;t need you to compromise on privacy, why not to switch to
    Signal.
&lt;/p&gt;
		</content>
    
    <author>
			<name>Exeami</name>
			<email>contact@exeami.com</email>
		</author>
  </entry>
</feed>

